Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, Duke University, Durham, North Carolina
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- [Chronological], 1850-1855; duk.00066; xxx.00052; prose 1 leaf, with 2 pasted-on attachments handwritten
  A manuscript that consists of a backing sheet with two smaller manuscripts scraps pasted on. On both the rectos of the paste-ons and on the backing sheet, Whitman discusses the conception of time beginning in "the Christian era." The verso of the bottom paste-on contains prose lines which appear to be related to what became section 2 of the poem ultimately titled I Sing the Body Electric, first published untitled in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. It appeared revised as Poem of the Body in the 1856 Leaves, before it appeared in its present nine-section version, as I Sing the Body Electric, in the 1867 edition. The scrap describes firemen "returning slowly home" from a fire, an image which suggests the description of "the march of firemen" and "the slow return from the fire" in I Sing the Body Electric. This suggests that the lines were written not later than 1855.
- [is rougher than it was], 1848; duk.00786; xxx.00480; MS f 129; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript page containing notes from Whitman's trip to New Orleans in 1848. This portion of the notes describes the trip across the Great Lakes and into Buffalo and Albany, New York. The notes would later be used as the basis for an article entitled New Orleans in 1848 that appeared in the New Orleans Picayune on January 25, 1887. It would later be reprinted in November Boughs. On the verso are manuscript notes about Whitman's family history, likely written in the mid-1850s.
- [myself to celebrate], 1850-1855; duk.00787; xxx.00048; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript containing lines included in the poem ultimately titled Song of Myself, including the poem's famous opening, "I celebrate myself." Song of Myself first appeared untitled in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ). The poem was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 Leaves, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves. On the verso is a prose manuscript with an unknown connection to Whitman's published work, in which he compares and contrasts writing to the composition of a "grand opera." In the repository, this manuscript is bound, seemingly by a collector, with a printer's copy of the 1881-82 edition of Leaves of Grass that contains numerous handwritten corrections by Whitman.
- [It were unworthy a live man to pray], 1850-1855; duk.00162; xxx.00048; MS q 203; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  An early scrap of prose material similar to parts of Song of Myself, which first appeared untitled in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ). The poem was first titled, Poem of Walt Whitman, an American, in the 1856 edition, and Whitman shortened the title to Walt Whitman in 1860–1861. The final title, Song of Myself, was not introduced until the 1881–1882 edition of Leaves. The manuscript's final three lines contributed to what became section 32, in which Whitman describes wanting to "live awhile with animals" because "[t]hey do not sweat and whine about their condition, / They do not lie awake in the dark and weep for their sins." These lines were present in the first version of the poem in 1855, suggesting a date of before or early in that year. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [On the other side], 1855-1858; duk.00241; xxx.00844; MS q 206; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A partial draft of what appears to be a self-review of Leaves of Grass. Whitman published numerous anonymous self-reviews throughout his life, and this scrap contains language similar to several extant reviews, in which Whitman references his own "barbaric yawp" and makes a clear distinction between that which is new and powerful (represented by his own poetry) from that which is old and stilted (previous poetic traditions). The time and location of publication is unknown, but Edward Grier notes that the Collins steamship line, which Whitman references, ceased operating in 1858, suggesting that this is likely a review for the 1855 or 1856 edition of Leaves (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York University Press, 1984] 1:336).
- [Health does not tell], Before or during 1856; duk.00789; xxx.00411; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A scrap of prose that contains a line that would appear in a poem in the 1856 and 1860–1861 editions of Leaves of Grass. The line, "Which is the poem or any book that is not diseased?," appeared in a slightly altered form in Poem of Many in One in 1856 and in Section 1 of Chants Democratic and Native American in 1860–1861. Although the poem would remain in Leaves in various forms until the final edition, the line was dropped after 1860–1861. An image of the verso is not available.
- [wooding at night], 1848; duk.00790; xxx.00480; MS q 111; prose 3 leaves handwritten
  Manuscript that deals with Whitman's return journey from New Orleans in 1848. Brief portions of these notes would find their way into an article entitled New Orleans in 1848 that appeared in the New Orleans Picayune on January 25, 1887. It would later be reprinted in November Boughs. The description of the "[l]ong monotonous stretch of the Mississippi" and the "[p]ainful effect of the excessive flatness of the country" were the portions that appeared, in an altered form, in the article.
- [A main part of the greatness], about 1857; duk.00152; xxx.00847; Box III-6A; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Handwritten notes about the ceaseless progression of humanity, most likely written in 1857. The scrap contains notes written in prose, with two poetic lines about the same subject written at the bottom of the page. The connection of these lines to any of Whitman's published poetry is unknown. An image of the verso is not available.
- for Dem Vistas, 1867-1870; duk.00126; xxx.00524; xxx.00851; MS 12mo 58; prose 3 leaves handwritten
  Although this manuscript is titled as a potential introduction or preface to Democratic Vistas or Memoranda during the War it never appeared in that format in either work. However, the thoughts it contains were echoed in an article that appeared in the St. Louis Dispatch on October 17, 1879. The article contained an interview with Whitman, in which he voiced ideas similar to those in the manuscript. A portion of the Dispatch piece would later be reprinted as An Interviewer's Item in Specimen Days and Complete Prose Works.
- pref to Dem Vistas, 1867-1870; duk.00791; xxx.00524; MS 12mo 58; prose 2 leaves handwritten
  A manuscript at the top of which Whitman has written "pref to Dem Vistas." However, the manuscript's connection to any published work is unknown.
- [the RR we go on], 1879; duk.00242; xxx.00803; xxx.00807; xxx.00852; xxx.00853; MS q 111; prose 8 leaves handwritten
  Pages of notes from Whitman's western railroad journey in September 1879. The pages describe his travels through Missouri and Kansas, and large portions of the notes would find their way into Specimen Days (specifically, the sections entitled Missouri State, Lawrence and Topeka, Kansas, Art Features, and A Silent Little Follower—The Coreopsis).
- Camden - Phila, 1884; duk.00121; xxx.00447; MS f 47; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript which contains lines similar to those found at the beginning of Additional Note, 1887, to English Edition 'Specimen Days.' The note was originally titled Additional Note. Written 1887 for the English Edition and included in the second (English) edition of Specimen Days. The note would later be reprinted in Complete Prose Works. The date on the manuscript, however, indicates that it was written in 1884 and likely intended for inclusion in a proposed two-volume edition of poetry and prose to be published in 1884. The edition never materialized. On the verso of the manuscript is a note by William Sloane Kennedy.
- [The American people ever], 1856; duk.00035; xxx.00610; MS 13; prose 2 leaves handwritten
  A manuscript about the California Vigilance Committee of the early and mid-1850s, these scraps contain lanuage similar to that found in Whitman's complete but unpublished essay The Eighteenth Presidency! The manuscript alludes to two of the candidates in the 1856 U.S. Presidential election, James Buchanan and Millard Fillmore, who Whitman refers to as "two old traitors," echoing a description of them as "two galvanized old men" in The Eighteenth Presidency!.
- [recommendation to the young], 1856; duk.00794; xxx.00610; MS 12mo 15; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A prose fragment dealing with political independence that contains phrases and ideas similar to those found in Whitman's complete but unpublished essay The Eighteenth Presidency! The essay was subtitled "Voice of Walt Whitman to each Young Man in the Naton, North, South, East, and West," a line which is echoed in this manuscript. The verso contains notes for poetry, including phrases which appear in section 6 of the final version of Starting from Paumanok, first published as Proto-Leaf in the 1860–1861 Leaves of Grass, and in Mediums, first published in the 1867 Leaves.
- [never to be forgotten in lectures], 1855-1860; duk.00795; xxx.00296; xxx.00411; MS 12mo 61; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A scrap of poetry with lines that contributed both to the poem ultimately titled Thoughts [Of these years I sing...] and to Apostroph, the opening section of Chants Democratic and Native American. Both poems first appeared in the 1860–1861 edition of Leaves of Grass. The verso contains prose about America's need for "her own poems."
- [Goethe], 1856; duk.00178; xxx.00560; MS q 80; prose 2 leaves handwritten
  Notes that Whitman made about Goethe. Unlike many of Whitman's other notes about authors, these notes seem to be based at least in part on his own observations rather than on secondary criticism. Some of the ideas contained in the scrap (particularly the final portion of the second leaf) found their way into Whitman's essay American National Literature, which appeared in the North American Review in March 1891, under the title Have We a National Literature? It was later reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ), under the title American National Literature before finally appearing in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Although the essay was not published until later, Edward Grier suggests that the manuscript dates from late 1856 (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York Univeristy Press, 1984] 5:1827). Pasted on the verso of the first page is a clipping from an article entitled The True Character of Goethe.
- [Russian serfs], 1855-1856; duk.00685; xxx.00110; Box II-5B 103; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Grouped with a collection of notes about Africa and Asia, this fragment notes that Russia "has 40 million of serfs, (or slaves)." With the paper suggesting a date of 1855 or 1856, this scrap may have been the impetus for Whitman's inclusion of "You Russian serf!" in his catalog of downtrodden peoples in Poem of Salutation in 1856; the poem would later be entitled Salut Au Monde! The reference to the "Russian serf" was dropped from the poem after the 1860 edition.
- [Africa Cape of Good Hope], 1855-1856; duk.00686; xxx.00110; Box II-5B 103; prose 2 leaves handwritten
  Grouped with a collection of notes about Africa and Asia, these two leaves contain notes about geographic locations and features, mostly in Africa. Many of the place names are included in the 1856 poem Poem of Salutation, later retitled Salut Au Monde! At least two longer lines from the manuscript also find their way into that poem: "fresh-sunned Mediterranean, and from one to another of its islands" (becoming "clear-sunned" in the poem) and "black venerable vast mother, the Nile."
- [Poem among the Siamese], 1854-1856; duk.00050; xxx.00906; MS 158; prose 1 leaf handwritten print
  A leaf of paper with several clippings pasted to it, as well as handwritten comments by Whitman. The clippings deal with Siamese proverbs and poems, as well as "the absurd chronology of the Hindoos." Whitman's handwritten comment at the top of page indicates that he may have been considering a poem entitled Poem among the Siamese. At the bottom of the page is a chunk of text which may be a draft poetic line or else notes about possible elements to include in the poem. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- Italian singers in America, 1858-1859; duk.00139; xxx.00907; MS 66; prose 3 leaves handwritten
  A manuscript containing a fairly neat draft of what is likely a piece of journalism that was never published. The piece deals with Italian opera singers in New York, a subject about which Whitman had already written in an article entitled The Opera, which appeared in Life Illustrated on November 10, 1855. As Edward Grier notes, the date of this manuscript is either late 1858 or 1859, as Marietta Piccolomini (a singer mentioned in the piece as being "the present 'rage'") only appeared in America during that opera season (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York Univeristy Press, 1984] 1:396).
- [The mob, the trial of Warren Hastings], 1870-1888; duk.00141; xxx.00486; MS q 36; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript with heavily-edited draft lines from Whitman's essay Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, which first appeared in November Boughs in 1888. The essay was also included in Complete Prose Works in 1892. Hicks (1748-1830) was a Quaker preacher and abolitionist who Whitman greatly admired.
- [The Old World], 1890; duk.00142; xxx.00569; MS f 37; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A partial draft of Whitman's essay Shakespeare for America, which was first published in the magazine Poet-Lore on September 15, 1890. The piece would later be reprinted in the Critic (titled Shakspere for America) on September 27, 1890, and then included in Whitman's Good-Bye My Fancy in 1891 and Complete Prose Works in 1892. On the verso is a letter from John W. Cook, dated 9 February 1890.
- A Word about Tennyson, 1886-1887; duk.00151; xxx.00468; MS q 49; prose 7 leaves handwritten print
  A complete draft of Whitman's essay A Word About Tennyson, which was first published in the Critic on January 1, 1887. The piece would later appear in the English edition of Democratic Vistas and Other Papers (1888), as well as November Boughs ( 1888 ) and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Whitman has numbered the pages and included a note to the printer at the top of the first leaf.
- [Though so loving], 1870-1881; duk.00183; xxx.00529; MS q 99; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Manuscript fragment comparing an unnamed poet (the repository finding aid suggests that it is Tennyson) to Walter Scott. It also contains a parenthetical description of Thomas Jefferson's assessment of Scott, a description which is echoed in Whitman's essay The Poetry of the Future, which was first published in the North American Review in February 1881. The essay would later be revised, reprinted, and retitled Poetry To-day in America—Shakspere—The Future in Specimen Days ( 1882 ) and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- [Mother's family lived], 1850; duk.00205; xxx.00910; MS f 128; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript containing autobiographical notes about Whitman's family history. Although Whitman never published any of these notes in his lifetime, they were used, in some cases word for word, in the biographical introduction to the multi-volume The Complete Writings of Walt Whitman, edited by Whitman's three literary executors and published in 1902. Horace Traubel, Richard Maurice Bucke, and Thomas Harned are listed as the authors of the introduction. Large portions of the recto are used nearly verbatim, but only certain phrases from the verso. The finding aid from the repository lists the date of this manuscript as 1850.
- How I get around at 60 and take notes, 1881; duk.00214; xxx.00911; MS 123; prose 11 leaves handwritten print
  A manuscript copy, with printer's instructions, of the first in a series of six articles that Whitman wrote for the Critic between January 1881 and July 1882, entitled How I Get Around at 60, and Take Notes (except for the sixth number, which was entitled How I Still Get Around at 60, and Take Notes). The article to which this manuscript contributed was published on January 29, 1881. A portion of the material for the article came from Winter Sunshine, which Whitman had published in the Philadelphia Times a year earlier. The article was later broken up and reprinted in various places throughout Specimen Days ( 1882 ).
- Specimen Days, about 1880; duk.00679; xxx.00870; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A small scrap on which Whitman has written "Specimen Days" at the top in red ink. The manuscript contains a short note about Giulia Grisi and Giuseppe Mario, two opera singers who Whitman saw in New York in the 1850s, and who Whitman mentions in the section of Specimen Days entitled Plays and Operas Too. Edward Grier dates the manuscript, based on the paper and ink, to around 1880 (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York Univeristy Press, 1984] 3:1064). The manuscript is pasted to a backing sheet, making the verso inaccessible.
- [A poem theme], 1850-1860; duk.00707; xxx.00935; Box II-5B 102; prose 1 leaf handwritten print
  A green scrap of paper with a brief note about a potential theme for a poem: "Be happy." Below the note is pasted a newspaper clipping with a story attributed to Aristotle. There is no known connection between the note or the clipping to Whitman's published poetry or prose. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [There is that], 1860-1870; duk.00809; xxx.00828; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A small scrap of prose that would make its way into a footnote for Carlyle From American Points of View, which was first printed in Specimen Days ( 1882-1883 ). Although Edward Grier states that the handwriting on the scrap indicates a date in the 1860s, the essay was not published until its inclusion in Specimen Days.